<class>
	<!-- 职业名 -->
	<name>Warlock</name>
	<!-- 如果有需要多选一的职业特性，把选项的总称写在这里 -->
	<options>Eldritch Pact</options>
	<!-- 不解释 -->
	<armorProficiencies>Cloth, leather</armorProficiency>
	<!-- 不解释 -->
	<weaponProficiencies>Simple melee, simple ranged</weaponProficiencies>
	<!-- 不能使用implement的职业可以删掉下面一行 -->
	<implement>Rods, wands</implement>
	<!-- 本职业独有的class feature写在这里，通常就是Class Features那一栏里的内容 -->
	<features>
		<!-- 每个class feature写在单独的<feature></feature>里面 -->
		<feature>
			<!-- 名字 -->
			<name>Eldritch Blast</name>
			<!-- 文字描述 -->
			<desc>All warlocks know the eldritch blast at-will power. This power can be used as a basic attack. You gain this power as well as another at-will power as determined by your Eldritch Pact.</desc>
			<!-- 如果这个feature赠送power的话就这样写。encounter和daily的写法参见cleric.xml -->
			<grantsPower>
				<!-- 赠送的power名 -->
				<name>Eldritch Blast</name>
				<!-- cd，只能是下面三种：at-will、encounter、daily -->
				<cooldown>at-will</cooldown>
			</grantsPower>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Prime Shot</name>
			<desc>If none of your allies are nearer to your target than you are, you receive a +1 bonus to ranged attack rolls against that target.</desc>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Shadow Walk</name>
			<desc>On your turn, if you move at least 3 squares away from where you started your turn, you gain concealment until the end of your next turn.</desc>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Warlock’s Curse</name>
			<!-- 如果描述多于一行则每一自然段占一行，行尾加/。最后一行的末尾不要加/ -->
			<desc>
				Once per turn as a minor action, you can place a Warlock’s Curse on the enemy nearest to you that you can see. A cursed enemy is more vulnerable to your attacks. If you hit a cursed enemy with an attack, you deal extra damage. You decide whether to apply the extra damage after making the damage roll. You can deal this extra damage once per round, so if you have dealt Warlock’s Curse damage since the start of your turn, you cannot deal it again until the start of your next turn./
				A Warlock’s Curse remains in effect until the end of the encounter or until the cursed enemy drops to 0 hit points or fewer./
				You can place a Warlock’s Curse on multiple targets over the course of an encounter; each curse requires the use of a minor action. You can’t place a Warlock’s Curse on a creature that is already affected by your or another character’s Warlock’s Curse./
				As you advance in level, your extra damage increases./
				 1st–10th +1d6/
				11th–20th +2d6/
				21st–30th +3d6
			</desc>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Fey Pact</name>
			<!-- 如果这个feature属于一个多选一的feature，把它从属的feature写在这里 -->
			<belongsToOption>Eldritch Pact</belongsToOption>
			<desc>
				You have forged a bargain with ancient, amoral powers of the Feywild. Some are primitive earth spirits, grim and menacing; some are capricious wood, sky, or water spirits; and others are incarnations of seasons or natural forces who roam the faerie realm like wild gods. They bestow magic that ranges from feral and savage to wondrous and enchanting.
				Eyebite: You know the eyebite spell.
				Misty Step: You have the Misty Step pact boon. You instantly transform into silver mist that streams a short distance and reforms, allowing you to flee or maneuver to set up a deadly attack.
				When an enemy under your Warlock’s Curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, you can immediately teleport 3 squares as a free action.
			</desc>
			<grantsPower>
				<name>Eyebite</name>
				<cooldown>at-will</cooldown>
			</grantsPower>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Fey Pact</name>
			<belongsToOption>Eldritch Pact</belongsToOption>
			<desc>
				You have forged a bargain with ancient, amoral powers of the Feywild. Some are primitive earth spirits, grim and menacing; some are capricious wood, sky, or water spirits; and others are incarnations of seasons or natural forces who roam the faerie realm like wild gods. They bestow magic that ranges from feral and savage to wondrous and enchanting./
				Eyebite: You know the eyebite spell./
				Misty Step: You have the Misty Step pact boon. You instantly transform into silver mist that streams a short distance and reforms, allowing you to flee or maneuver to set up a deadly attack./
				When an enemy under your Warlock’s Curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, you can immediately teleport 3 squares as a free action.
			</desc>
			<grantsPower>
				<name>Eyebite</name>
				<cooldown>at-will</cooldown>
			</grantsPower>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Infernal Pact</name>
			<belongsToOption>Eldritch Pact</belongsToOption>
			<desc>
				Long ago a forgotten race of devils created a secret path to power and taught it to the tieflings of old to weaken their fealty to Asmodeus. In his wrath, Asmodeus destroyed the scheming devils and struck their very names from the memory of all beings—but you dare to study their perilous secrets anyway./
				Hellish Rebuke: You know the hellish rebuke spell./
				Dark One’s Blessing: You have the Dark One’s Blessing pact boon. You instantly gain vitality from a cursed enemy when that enemy falls./
				When an enemy under your Warlock’s Curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, you immediately gain temporary hit points equal to your level.
			</desc>
			<grantsPower>
				<name>Hellish Rebuke</name>
				<cooldown>at-will</cooldown>
			</grantsPower>
		</feature>
		<feature>
			<name>Star Pact</name>
			<belongsToOption>Eldritch Pact</belongsToOption>
			<desc>
				You have mastered the astrologer’s art, learning the secret names of the stars and gazing into the Far Realm beyond, gaining great power thereby. You can call upon powers that madden or terrify your enemies, manipulate chance and fate, or scour your foes with icy banes and curses drawn from beyond the night sky./
				Dire Radiance: You know the dire radiance spell./
				Fate of the Void: You have the Fate of the Void pact boon. Your curse intermingles with the lost vitality of a cursed enemy to reveal a glimpse of the future to you./
				When an enemy under your Warlock’s Curse is reduced to 0 hit points or fewer, you gain a +1 bonus to any single d20 roll you make during your next turn (attack roll, saving throw, skill check, or ability check). If you don’t use this bonus by the end of your turn, it is lost./
				This bonus is cumulative; if three cursed enemies drop to 0 hit points or fewer before your next turn, you gain a +3 bonus to a d20 roll during your turn.
			</desc>
			<grantsPower>
				<name>Dire Radiance</name>
				<cooldown>at-will</cooldown>
			</grantsPower>
		</feature>
	</features>
</class>